Guide to the New-York Historical Society Pictorial Archive 1804-2009 (bulk 1900s-1970s) NYHS-RG 5
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society pictorial archive
1804-2009 (bulk 1900s-1970s)
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 5
30.63 Linear feet in 29 document boxes and 41 boxes of negatives, and oversize folders
The New-York Historical Society Pictorial Archive (NYHS-RG 5) primarily includes photographs of N-YHS's buildings, galleries and other interior spaces, exhibitions, collection objects, programs, and people, such as trustees, officers, and staff. Portions of the record group have been digitized and can be viewed on flickr.
Scope and Content Note
The New-York Historical Society Pictorial Archive (NYHS-RG 5) primarily includes images of N-YHS's buildings, galleries and other interior spaces, exhibitions, collection objects, programs, and people, such as trustees, officers, and staff. The bulk of the images date roughly from the early 1900s into the 1970s, though there are images from earlier and later periods. Most of the record group includes black and white photographic prints, but there are also negatives, color slides, and some color prints. There are also a relatively small number of non-photographic formats, including drawings, posters, and architectural plans for building renovations after 1965.
Many of the photographic prints found in the record group have a control number noted on the back; this number corresponds to negatives, many of which are still extant and found in Series XI. The envelopes holding the negatives often include descriptive information that goes beyond that found with the print.
There are many highlights in the record group. The Buildings series includes rich sets of photographs documenting the construction of the Central Park West building in the early 1900s and the major expansion of 1937-1938. There are many photographs of galleries, the library, and other spaces in both the Central Park West building and N-YHS's earlier home on 2nd Avenue and 11th Street. The Exhibitions series includes installation and related object and publicity photographs. Photographs for exhibitions and programs also include the opening receptions and other events held at N-YHS, such as the annual Strawberry and St. Nicholas festivals, Eleanor Roosevelt attending the 1952 Votes for Women exhibition, and noted clown Emmett Kelly attending the 1968 exhibition Circus Posters from the Days of the Big Top. The Staff Events and Trustees, Officers and Staff series provide glimpses of some of the people from N-YHS over the years.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Historical Note
Timeline of Homes of N-YHS
1804-1809 The City Hall, Northside of Wall Street at the head of Broad Street
1809-1816 The Government House, Facing Bowling Green
1816-1832 New York Institution, in City Hall Park
1832-1837 Remsen Building, Southwest corner of Broadway at Chambers Street
1837-1841 Stuyvesant Institute, 639 Broadway opposite Bond Street
1841-1857 New York University, East Side of Washington Square
1857-1908 170 Second Avenue, Southeast corner of 11th Street
1908-present 170 Central Park West at 77th Street
History of N-YHS:
"For without the aid of historic records and authentic documents, history would be nothing more than a well-combined series of ingenious conjectures and amusing fables." From an 1805 address of the New-York Historical Society
The New-York Historical Society is New York's oldest museum. At the time of the Society's founding in 1804, only 75,000 people lived in New York City, Alexander Hamilton had just been killed in a duel with Aaron Burr, and New York still spelled its name with a hyphen (thus the hyphen in the museum's name). On November 20, 1804, merchant John Pintard met with ten other New Yorkers to create an organization that would, according to its Constitution, "collect and preserve whatever may relate to the natural, civil, or ecclesiastical History of the United States in general and of this State in particular." This was a broad mission statement but since there were very few museums at the time, and only one other historical society in the nation, the founders decided it was imperative to collect an inclusive range of materials before they were lost.
The first meetings of the Society were held rent free in City Hall because New York City's mayor, DeWitt Clinton, was a founding member. The Society's library grew significantly in 1809 when Pintard sold his own book and manuscript collection to the New-York Historical Society. As the library and museum continued to grow, its members soon realized that it needed a home. Unable to find a permanent space, the Society moved five times between 1809 and 1857, until it was able to construct its own building on Second Avenue and Eleventh Street.
In the mid-19th century, the Society's membership increased along with its library and art collections. Between 1858-1867, the Society acquired the collection of the New York Gallery of Fine Arts, the Abbott collection of Egyptian Artifacts (now at the Brooklyn Museum), and 433 watercolor paintings of John James Audubon. Soon the art and the library were competing for space and it became apparent that the Society had once again outgrown its home. In 1908, N-YHS moved into a newly constructed building at its present location at 77th Street and Central Park West. Renovations in the 1930's added two new wings and a fifteen-story stack area to the building. Today, the museum and library continue to provide access to collections relating to the political, legal, cultural, mercantile, and social history of the United States and New York in particular.
For more detailed history see: Vail, R.W.G. Knickerbocker birthday: a sesqui-centennial history of the New York Historical Society, 1804-1954. New York: New York Historical Society, 1954.
Administrative History of the Pictorial Archive
The specific source of the pictorial archive is uncertain, but the bulk of it appears to have been compiled from various sources, mostly N-YHS in-house photographers, but also outside sources. The archive was likely compiled by the staff of N-YHS's Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections, known as the Print Room. The pictorial archive as it existed in 1998 was documented in Helena Zinkham A Guide to Print, Photograph, Architecture & Ephemera Collections; it is recorded as PR 46 at page 114.
Since 1998, the Pictorial Archive was transferred into N-YHS's institutional archive, and assigned a new call number (NYHS-RG 5). Although the core content of the Pictorial Archive appears to have remained consistent over recent decades, the arrangement and description of the content has changed somewhat over time. Also, additional material has continued to be integrated into the Pictorial Archive, while some material, especially architectural plans and Field Exploration Committee negatives, have been moved to other record groups within N-YHS's institutional archive. Going forward from 2015, the Pictorial Archive is expected to continue to accrue additional images, but not in a centralized manner as in the past. Most images collected in the future are expected to be archived with their department or other such contextual records.
Related Material
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives).
Accruals Note
The Pictorial Archive will occasionally receive accruals of new material, although most photographs and other images are expected to be retained in the future with their contextual documents within a record group associated with the department creating the images.
Existence and Location of Copies Note
Some of the images in the Pictorial Archive have been digitized and can be viewed on flickr. The user should be aware that the box and folder numbers associated with certain images on flickr may no longer be precisely accurate because of additional processing done in 2015 with the photographs.
A large number of deteriorating negatives documenting the 1937-1938 expansion and renovation of Central Park West were digitized in 2015 by Eleanor Gillers. Information about the digital versions can be found in the Series I (Buildings) description, specifically at the folders concerning the expansion. Other than the digital versions, Series I (Buildings) holds prints of many, though not all, of the original negatives.
Arrangement Note
The New-York Historical Society Pictorial Archive is organized in the following series:
Series I: Buildings
Series II: Exhibitions
Series III: School Programs
Series IV: Public Programs
Series V: Events & Publicity
Series VI: Staff Events
Series VII: Trustees, Officers & Staff
Series VIII: (Series not used)
Series IX: Object Images
Series X: Architectural Plans and Drawings
Series XI: Negatives
New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- Photographs.; negatives (photographs); Photographic prints.; Portraits.; Posters.; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Libraries and institutions -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Museum buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Drawings.; Museum buildings -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; Museum exhibits -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; New-York Historical Society -- Archives.; New-York Historical Society -- Buildings.; New-York Historical Society -- Employees.; New-York Historical Society -- Photographs.; Walker & Gillette; York & Sawyer
- Series I: Buildings, 1804-2009; 5.16 Linear feet
  Scope and Content
  This series primarily includes photographs of N-YHS's building on Central Park West (1909-present) and, to a lesser extent, its earlier home on 2nd Avenue (1857-1909). There are photographs of the Central Park West building from both before and after the major expansion and renovation of the building in 1937-1938. Both the early twentieth century and 1930s construction projects at Central Park West are documented. The series includes both interior and exterior views.
  The series also includes a small number of images of N-YHS's various homes from 1804 to 1857. And the series includes images of Richard Morris Hunt's proposals of the 1860s for a building in Central Park for N-YHS and of the summer museum N-YHS maintained at the Thompson homestead on Long Island from 1942-1946.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically. This translates roughly into an arrangement by building, then topically within building.
  Related Archival Materials Note
  Textual documents and architectural plans and drawings related to the construction of the 2nd Avenue and Central Park West buildings are found in the New-York Historical Society original buildings planning & construction records (NYHS-RG 3). A small number of photographs are also found in that record group.
  - Early N-YHS Homes, [1804-1866] (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents Note
    Includes photographs of prints and drawings of N-YHS's first several homes and of Richard M. Hunt's drawings for a building in Central Park for N-YHS (1860s).
  - New York University, Washington Square, circa 1890? (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 2)
    Includes an oversize photograph of NYU's building, demolished in 1894, that was N-YHS's home from 1841-1857.
  - Richard Morris Hunt. Three Designs for Proposed Historical Museum, circa 1866 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 9)
    Includes three photoreproductions of Hunt's proposals to the N-YHS Building Committee for the design of a building in Central Park.
  - 170 Second Ave. Exterior, 1862-1908 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 170 Second Ave. Interior (1 of 2), Late 1800s?-1908 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 170 Second Ave. Interior (2 of 2), Late 1800s?-1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 170 Second Avenue. Exterior & Interior, Oversize, Late 1800s?-circa 1908? (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 12)
  - 170 Central Park West. View of Future N-YHS Site, 1887? (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 170 Central Park West. York and Sawyer, architects, at future site, 1902 September 10 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 5)
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. Central Portion (1 of 5), 1903-1906 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes cornerstone ceremony (1903) and photograph of Robert Kelby, Henry Dexter, and Samuel Hoffman (1905).
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. Central Portion (2 of 5), 1903-1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. Central Portion (3 of 5), 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Includes photographs taken on a monthly basis from March 1905 to November 1906 showing construction progress on the exterior. These correspond to the photos in the following scrapbook.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. Central Portion (4 of 5). Scrapbook, 1905-1906 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. Central Portion (5 of 5), 1905-1906 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. Central Portion. Cornerstone Laying, 1903 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 11)
    Includes oversize photographs of event.
  - 170 Central Park West. Exterior, ca. 1908-1937 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 170 Central Park West. Exterior, Oversize, circa 1910-1936 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 10)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior, ca. 1908-1937 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Mounted Oversize Prints of Reading Room and Galleries, circa 1910-1936 (Box 71, Folder 1)
  - 170 Central Park West. Annexes 1 and 2 (Townhouses), 1932-1938 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes exterior photographs of the townhouses at 5 West 76th Street (former Oscar Strauss residence) and 4 West 77th Street (former Louis Fleischmann residence), known as Annex 1 and Annex 2 respectively, and the Marine History gallery in Annex 2. See also the folders of pre-1937 Central Park West exterior and 1937 wing construction photographs as they also include some views of the townhouses. The folder also includes photos of #7, 9, 11, 13 W. 76th street, which were purchased during construction, and some views of their demolition for the garden.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. New Wings (1 of 6), 1937 January-March (Box 2, Folder 5)
    This folder and the following three include photographic prints documenting the 1937-38 expansion. The photographs are sequentially numbered, in chronological order, beginning with a prefix of "BU." This first folder holds the prints of negatives BU1 to BU48, with some gaps.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. New Wings (2 of 6), 1937 April-June (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Includes prints of negatives BU49 to BU95.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. New Wings (3 of 6), 1937 July-September 15 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Includes prints of negatives BU96 to BU134, with gaps.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. New Wings (4 of 6), 1937 September 22-1938 March (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes prints of negatives BU135 to BU173, with gaps.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. New Wings (5 of 6), 1937-1939 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    This folder includes photographic prints documenting the 1937-38 expansion as it impacted the existing interior spaces in mid-1937. The photographs are sequentially numbered, in chronological order, beginning with a prefix of "IN." The prints are numbered BU1 to BU48, with some gaps.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. New Wings (6 of 6), 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    The bulk of the acetate negatives for the photographs in the above five folders were in a deteriorated condition and all but about 24 were discarded in 2016. Prior to discard, all the negatives were scanned. This folder includes the inventory of the digitized negatives and the related filename for the images. There were negatives for which there is no print in the above folders and only the digital image remains. Some of the negatives having a prefix of BU were enclosed in envelopes that had descriptive captions recorded on them; this folder also includes those envelopes. Envelopes with no captions or other information were discarded.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. Lighting, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Includes mostly snapshots of published images of museum and library spaces (not N-YHS) with captions on reverse referring to the lighting. A few snapshots of an N-YHS gallery under construction, and a photograph of George Zabriskie in England dated August 1937, suggest that these might be images compiled by Alexander Wall and Zabriskie during their summer 1937 inquiry into state of the art lighting practices for museums.
  - 170 Central Park West. Construction. New York Building Congress, 1938 April 19 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Includes a photograph of the award ceremony honoring the craftsmen who worked on the expansion.
  - 170 Central Park West. World War II Response, 1942-1944 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes photographs of the Red Cross staff and surgical dressings unit at N-YHS, and the top floor gallery with precautions taken against incendiary bombs.
  - Thompson Homestead Memorial, East Hampton, Long Island, 1942-1945 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Includes photographs of the summer museum maintained by N-YHS from 1942-1945, including images of the 1942 dedication and reception, exterior views, and interior exhibitions.
  - 170 Central Park West. Exterior (1 of 2), circa 1939-1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Includes photographs of the full-length exterior of the building, some taken from within Central Park. Photographs from 1999 include a contact sheet with related negatives.
  - 170 Central Park West. Exterior (2 of 2), circa 1939-1999 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Includes exterior details, including the garden, doors, bus stop, skylights, and views of Central Park from the roof. The folder includes a contact sheet with related negatives.
  - 170 Central Park West. Exterior. Water Main Repair, 1975 February (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Includes photographs of the repair work beneath the sidewalk at N-YHS's front entrance. See also Series II. Exhibitions: New York, The New Empire: John Pintard and his Society; that folder includes contact sheets and negatives that hold images for both the water main break and the exhibition.
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior/Exterior Photographed by Anne Day, 1984-1986 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Library (1 of 2), ca. 1930s-1982 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Library (2 of 2), circa 2000s (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Galleries and Installations (1 of 3), 1930s-1980s? (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Galleries and Installations (2 of 3), 1930s-1980s? (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Galleries and Installations (3 of 3), 1930s-1980s? (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Beekman Rooms, 1940-1947, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Port of New York Gallery (1 of 2), circa 1957 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Port of New York Gallery (2 of 2). Oversize, 1948 (Box 70, Folder 4)
    Includes pencil drawings of the gallery by Edward Caswell.
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Auditorium, 1937-circa 2000? (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Work Areas, 1930s-1989 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Includes photographs of the bindery, conservation, Print Room (one with Bella Landauer), object storage areas, book stacks, carpentry shop, and other work areas, some with staff.
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Construction of Period Rooms, 1950 December (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. General, 1986-1988, 2009 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - 170 Central Park West. Drawings and Etchings, circa 1940, circa 1980s? (Box 70, Folder 2)
    Includes copies of an etching by E. Roth (1940) and a ink drawing by Roxie Munro (1980s?) of the building exterior.
  - 170 Central Park West. Drawing by Paul Chiasson, 1983 (Drawer 12A-B10, Folder 15)
    Includes a drawing by Chiasson of the building's front elevation
  - 170 Central Park West. Interior. Floor and Room Plans, Undated (Box 70, Folder 3)
    Includes a drawing of floor plans for visitors to the building, comparative 1860 and 1942 schematic floor plans, and drawings by F&H of furniture and furniture placement for the Trustee's Room.
- Series II: Exhibitions, 1932-2000; 8.23 Linear feet
  This series includes images related to various exhibitions that N-YHS held, mostly from the 1940s until the early 1990s. The images primarily include specific objects used in the exhibitions and installation views. There are some images of opening receptions and other events tied to the exhibition. The content is uneven across the series as some exhibitions are heavily represented with images, while others, especially in the earliest years, include fewer images, sometimes only signage. Most of the images are undated and unidentified and so are associated with particular exhibitions often only through their folder labeling, which has been retained as found.
  The bulk of the images in the series are black and white photographic prints. Some of the files also include other formats, especially negatives and color slides, which are noted at the folder level. Some of the files also include press releases, captions, and other such textual matter. The series includes some non-photographic pictorial matter, including exhibition publicity posters.
  The Exhibitions series is arranged chronologically and by title of the exhibition. References to months in the date range are to the exhibition opening. Some folders include material from more than one exhibition. A few folders of material related to exhibitions installed in venues other than the N-YHS building are at the end of the series, as are folders of oversize posters.
  - Annex 2 (4 West 77th St.) Exhibitions: Ships & Steamboats; Old New York, 1932-1933 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - N-YHS 135th Anniversary, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - John Paul Jones; Presidential Campaigns; Emma Thursby Memorial, 1940-1941 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Allied Artists of America; The New York Stage from the 1880s, 1942 October-November (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Latin Americana, 1944 January (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - World of Washington Irving, 1944 October (Box 5, Folder 6)
    Includes a publicity flier for the exhibition.
  - Army Air Forces: Wings Over the Central Pacific, 1945 January (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - The Swedish Nightingale: The Jenny Lind Collection, 1945 October (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Includes the program and press release for the opening.
  - The Birds of America: Audubon's Original Watercolors, 1946 January (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Historic Hudson; American Presentation Silver, 1946-1947 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - News Artists to the American People: The Harry T. Peters Collection, 1947 February (Box 5, Folder 11)
    See also the oversize folders of exhibition posters.
  - Big Snows; Doctors of Old New York: Centennial of the New York Academy of Medicine, 1947 March (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Trinity Church 250th Anniversary; Recent Accessions; Frederic Remington, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - American Quilts; Gold Fever; Up From the Cradle: American Portraits of Children, 1948 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Bookplates (Oliver Clement Sheean Collection); Our City Hall in History, 1949 October (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Gramercy Park, 1949 December (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Sketches of 20th Century New York by Vernon Howe Bailey; Erie Canal, "Mother of Cities"; Fire Department Exhibition, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    Includes publicity shots for Fire Prevention Week taken at the Fire Department exhibition.